His triumph changed the world forever.
Gandhi is a drama, history film directed by Richard Attenborough.
In the early years of the 20th century, Mohandas K.
Gandhi, a British-trained lawyer, forsakes all worldly
possessions to take up the cause of Indian independence.
Faced with armed resistance from the British government, Gandhi adopts a policy of 'passive
resistance', endeavouring to win freedom for his people without resorting to bloodshed.
Mahatma Gandhi, played by Ben Kingsley.
Margaret Bourke-White, played by Candice Bergen.
General Dyer, played by Edward Fox.
Lord Irwin, played by John Gielgud.
Judge Broomfield, played by Trevor Howard.
Lord Chelmsford, played by John Mills.
Gandhi is a 1982 biographical film directed and produced by
Richard Attenborough and written by John Briley.
It is based on the life of Mahatma Gandhi (portrayed by Ben Kingsley), a major leader in the
Indian independence movement against the British Empire during the 20th century.
It covers Gandhi's life from a defining moment in 1893, as he is thrown off a South African train for
being in a whites-only compartment and concludes with his assassination and funeral in 1948.
Although a practising Hindu, Gandhi's embracing of other faiths,
particularly Christianity and Islam, is also depicted.
Over 300,000 extras appeared in the film, believed
to be the most in any film made.
Gandhi was released by Columbia Pictures in India on 30 November 1982, in the
United Kingdom on 3 December, and in the United States on 8 December.
It was praised for its portrayal of the life of Gandhi, the Indian independence
movement, and the deleterious results of British colonisation on India.
It was considered to have maintained a reasonable level of historical accuracy, although many separate events were amalgamated, such
as historical meetings with individual people being combined into single fictionalized scenes for narrative pacing.
Several events were exaggerated or invented, such as being beaten
by police while burning registration certificates.
The chronology of Gandhi's early activism was altered, and certain historical
figures (such as Christian missionary and independence activist C.F.
Andrews and founder of Pakistan Mohammad Ali Jinnah) were
considered to have been portrayed inaccurately.
The film was praised for conveying Gandhi's core principles of nonviolence and human dignity
effectively, providing an accessible introduction to his life and message.
Its production values, costume design, and Kingsley's
performance received worldwide critical acclaim.
It became a commercial success, grossing $127.8 million on a $22 million budget.
It received a leading eleven nominations at the 55th Academy Awards, winning eight,
including Best Picture, Best Director, and Best Actor (for Kingsley).
The British Film Institute ranked it as the 34th
greatest British film of the 20th century.
The American Film Institute ranked the film 29th on
its list of most inspiring movies.
The film explores themes of muslim, strike, prayer, freedom, independence.
The tone is dark and emotional.